<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two discourses introductory to a disquisition demonstrating the unlawfulness of the marriage of cousin Germans, from law, reason, Scripture, and antiquity by John Turner ...</title>
            <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11417</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13298489</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13298489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98910</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63921)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98910)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 440:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two discourses introductory to a disquisition demonstrating the unlawfulness of the marriage of cousin Germans, from law, reason, Scripture, and antiquity by John Turner ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 63 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.H. for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consanguinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Consanguinity (Law) --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98910:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98910:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO DISCOURSES INTRODUCTORY TO A DISQUISITION Demonſtrating the UNLAWFULNESS OF THE MARRIAGE OF <hi>Couſin Germans;</hi> From Law, Reaſon, Scripture, and Antiquity. By <hi>JOHN T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNER,</hi> late Fellow of <hi>Chriſts Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Opinionum commenta delet dies, Naturae judicia confirmat.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. H.</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops Head</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard. 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98910:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98910:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Deſign of the two following Diſcourſes is expreſs'd in the Title-page, and how they contribute to that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, will be beſt ſeen by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes themſelves. I do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs very ſolemnly, whatever In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations may be made, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this Introduction, or of thoſe Diſcourſes which are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to follow it; yet I would not, upon any Conſideration whatſoever, have publiſhed my Thoughts upon this Subject, did
<pb facs="tcp:98910:3"/> I not think my ſelf obliged in Conſcience to do it; did I not know certainly, that what I am about to write, aims not at the Embroilment, and Diſturbance, but at the Peace of the World; and were I not equally ſure, that all this may be done upon ſuch Principles, as can give no man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſonable cauſe of Offence, but on the contrary, ſuch as with which, all Wiſe, and Good Men ought to be extreamly ſatisfied and pleaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98910:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the true Meaning and Intention of the Statute of <hi>32. H. VIII. c. 38.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. THE Act of Parliament ſtill in force concerning this Aſſair, which though repealed <hi>1mo. &amp; 2do. Phil. &amp; Mar. c.</hi> 8. was again reſtored to its Ancient Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity <hi>1mo. Elizabethae c.</hi> 1. is 32. <hi>II. 8. c.</hi> 38.</p>
            <p n="2">II. In the Preface to that Act there are theſe words concerning the Inconveniencies of Diſpenſations to Marry, which had been uſed in former time to be procured of the Pope, in caſe the Parties concerned were allied to one another in any of the Degrees prohibited by the Canon Law.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Further alſo by reaſon of other Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions than Gods Law admitteth for their Lucre by that Court <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>The Court of</hi> Rome.</note> invented, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation whereof they always reſerved to themſelves, as in Kindred or Aſſinity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Couſin Germans;</hi> and ſo to fourth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98910:4"/> and fourth Degree, Carnal Knowledge of any of the ſame Kin or Affinity before in ſuch outward Degrees, which elſe were lawful, and be not prohibited by Gods Law, and all becauſe they would get Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. And our late Reverend and Learned Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> in his Miſcellaneous Diſcourſes, hath among other things, a Letter to a Friend in Reſolution of this Queſtion concerning the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> in which he determins on the Affirmative ſide, with what reaſon, we ſhall ſee in its due place; but that for which I now mentioned his Name, is that ſpeaking of this Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, he ſaith,<note place="margin">P. 267. Ed. 1673.</note> 
               <q rend="inline">That amongſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees ſpecified in that Act as lawful, if his Memory fail him not, <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> are expreſly mentioned.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. And his Memory did not fail him, though he made a wrong uſe of it at this Time; for though it be true that <hi>Couſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> are mentioned in the words above pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by me, as Parties lawfully marriage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with one another, and no ways prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by the Law of God, yet it is here to be conſidered, that this is not the Judgment of the Law it ſelf, but only of the men that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98910:4"/> made it, who may poſſibly be deceived, as the Articles of our Church oblige us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that even a General Council may err, notwithſtanding they lay claim to thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Aſſiſtances, to which no Parliament e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pretended; for theſe words are not in the very Act properly and ſtrictly ſo called, but only in the Preface to it, in which, as in all other Acts of Parliament, the Reaſons why that Act was made, are ſpecified and ſet down; but that which in the true, ſtrict, and legal Propriety is called the Act, and does oblige as the Act and Deed of the King, and his Two Houſes in Parliament Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, is of neceſſity to be ſuppoſed to begin at theſe words, <hi>Be it therefore Enacted by the King,</hi> &amp;c. and that only which follows theſe words (which otherwiſe would be in vain, and of no ſignification) is that which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth an Obligation upon the Subject.</p>
            <p n="5">V. It is therefore in the next place to be conſidered, what that is, which is by this Act of Parliament prohibited, after thoſe words, <hi>Be it Enacted by the King,</hi> &amp;c. and that is expreſſed in theſe following words, <hi>That—all and every ſuch Marriages as within this Church of</hi> England, <hi>ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted between lawful Perſons (as by this Act we declare all Perſons to be lawful,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98910:5"/> that be not prohibited by Gods Law, to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) ſuch Marriages being contracted and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnized in the Face of the Church, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate with bodily Knowledge,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall be by Authority of this preſent Parliament aforeſaid, deemed, judged, and taken to be lawful, good, juſt and indiſſoluble—and that no Reſervation or Prohibition, Gods Law only excepted, ſhall trouble or impeach any Marriage without the</hi> Levitical <hi>Degrees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. So that if we will ſubmit our ſelves to the Conduct and Guidance of that Clue, which this Act of Parliament hath given us for our Direction, the <hi>Levitical</hi> Degrees, that is to ſay, the Degrees prohibited or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> are to be the Meaſures of Liberty and Reſtraint; and whatſoever Degree the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> forbids, the ſame is forbidden by the Laws of <hi>England;</hi> and on the contrary, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Degrees are permitted in the Code of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the ſame are likewiſe allowed and deemed to be lawful, good, juſt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble by this Act of Parliament, and by the Civil Laws of this Nation.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Whence it is plain, that the true thing to be enquired into for a clear and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Reſolution of this weighty Queſtion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98910:5"/> the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> ſo far as this Act of Parliament is concerned in it, is this; what are thoſe Degrees which are prohibited by the Law of <hi>Moſes?</hi> And if it ſhall appear upon a juſt and impartial Survey of the whole matter, that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> was abſolutely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, unleſs in a Caſe, which ſhall be mentioned, in which our Age and Nation is not concerned, and in another which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth, nor can belong to perſons in a private Capacity and Station, in which Number I include all but Sovereign Princes, or ſuch as have a nigh Relation to the Crown, then it follows unavoidably, that in all ordinary Caſes ſuch Marriages are prohibited by this Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Neither will it be ſufficient in this Caſe to ſay, That the King and his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did not intend by this Act to prohibit the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> but on the contrary, their Intention was certainly to make it lawful, which I do readily grant; yet here, I ſpeak it with all Submiſſion to the Judgment of my betters, there are two ſeveral Intentions to be conſidered, a Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and a General; by a particular Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as appears by the Preface to the Act, it was deſigned to make it lawful for <hi>Couſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98910:6"/> to Marry, but the general intention conſiſted in theſe two things, firſt they deſigned to remove all the obſtructions of the Canon Law, and to make all thoſe Marriages to be good and Lawful, which had no other barr but that of <hi>Gregory</hi> or <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> and the Practice of thoſe Courts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> to which the Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of Marriages, whether Lawful or Unlawful, appertained.</p>
            <p>The ſecond general intention, beſides the ſhaking off the Yoak, and prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the frauds and abuſes of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſuch as were commiſſioned by him, was inſtead of the Canon Law, which made a trade of Inceſt, and would ſell the moſt grievous ſins for a Sum of Money, by adding <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to all their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions, <hi>niſi aliter Eccleſia diſpenſet,</hi> to ſubſtitute another meaſure in its ſtead, which meaſure was to be the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and therefore whatſoever degrees were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden in the <hi>Levitical</hi> Law, or in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Practice of the Church of God among the <hi>Jews,</hi> were likewiſe prohibited, forbidden, and made unlawful by this their ſecond general intention, which being the declared Meaſure of all particular inſtances, it is manifeſt they did intend to bind up, and reſtrain <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> from Marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98910:6"/> one another, if it ſhould appear at any time hereafter, though it did not then, that all ſuch Marriages were <hi>Levitically</hi> unlawful.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. But though this Act of Parliament ſhould in expreſs words, have given a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence for <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> to Marry, which it is very clear it hath not done, yet upon ſuppoſition that it was prohibited by the Law of God or of Nature, which is no leſs the voice of God then that of Revelation, it would ſtill have remained unlawful, for any Chriſtian Man or Woman to accept of this liberty which the Parliament had given, becauſe in all theſe caſes where the divine Prohibitions interfere with the liberties granted by human Laws, we are to obey God rather then men, and this may be lay'd down as a maxim of undoubted and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal truth, that human Laws may if they pleaſe ſtraiten the reſtraints, but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enlarge the liberties of mankind, beyond what the Laws of God or Nature do allow, which, beſides that the thing is very plain in it ſelf, and if it were otherwiſe there could be no ſtable and unalterable Nature of things, but the Nature of vertue and vice might be inverted by the variable hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of different times or men; I ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98910:7"/> this, this is no more, than what our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliaments have themſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd, for ſo ſpeaks that Auguſt and Venerable Aſſembly concerning inceſtuous and deteſtable conjunctions which were uſed to be diſpenſed with by the Authority of the See of <hi>Rome. 25. H. 8. c.</hi> 22. <q rend="inline">Which Marriages albeit they be plainly prohibited and deteſted by the Laws of God, yet nevertheleſs at ſometimes they have proceeded under Colours of diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, by mans Power which is but u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped, and of right ought not to be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, admitted, ne allowed, for no man of what eſtate, degree, or condition ſoever he be, hath power to diſpence with Gods Laws, as all the Clergy of this Realm—and the moſt part of all the famous Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of Chriſtendom, and we alſo do affirm and think.</q> Which very words are again repeated upon another occaſion. 28. <hi>H. 8. c.</hi> 7. And the Univerſities that did concur in opinion with the Parliament, and Church of <hi>England,</hi> beſides our own, the two moſt Learned and Judicious in the Chriſtian World, were the Univerſities of <hi>Bononia, Padua, Paris, Orleance, Tolouſe, Angiew,</hi> and divers others. <q rend="inline">To which were likewiſe added the private writings of many right excellent and well Learned
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98910:7"/> men.</q> As it is in the ſaid former Act in theſe very words expreſſed and declared, and it is likewiſe further to be conſidered that this very Act of 32 <hi>H. 8. c.</hi> 38. was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned only to aboliſh diſannul and repeal the Canon Law, and to make all thoſe Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages and conjunctions Lawful, which had no other barr, than the canonical Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions, founded upon the ſole Authority of the Pope, without the expreſs warranty of the Scripture it ſelf, but if there be any degrees that were Unlawful upon another account, whether it be of Nature or of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, it is the declared intention of this Act of Parliament, not to diſanul theſe Prohibitions, but to confirm them.</p>
            <p n="10">X. Which things being laid down and premiſed beforehand, for the greater clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of proceeding in this affair, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made thus plain, both what the Law of <hi>England</hi> determins in the caſe, and how far human Laws may be of force or may be complyed with in matters of this Nature, the next thing to be enquired into, is, what the Laws of God in the inſpired Writings either of the Old Teſtament or the New, have determined, or how the light of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which if appealed to without preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice or paſſion is the impartial Oracle of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98910:8"/> Truth and Juſtice, will decide this great queſtion, which hath exerciſed the Wits and Pens of ſo many Learned men, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lawfulneſs, or Unlawfulneſs of the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans;</hi> and that the arguments which I ſhall produce from the revealed Law of God, may have the greater force, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew that Nature and Revelation are conſiſtent to each other, and as I ſhall undeniably prove that the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> was Prohibited the <hi>Jews,</hi> and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, as I ſhall make it appear, is in a more eſpecial manner Unlawful to all Chriſtian People, ſo that we may ſee, that the reaſon of theſe Laws, and conſequently their obligation, is eternal, I will make my entrance upon the deciſion of this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, by enquiring how far the Laws of Nature are concerned in it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98910:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Laws of Nature, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their Obligation in the general.</head>
            <p n="1">I. BY the Laws of Nature are meant thoſe ſtanding rules of Life and Practice among men, which are of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Unalterable and Eternal Obligation; or they are ſuch Laws and Rules of life, as to the breach of which there is a natural puniſhment annexed. For to ſay a thing is eſſentially good or evil, to call it by hard names, and to affirm that it hath a natural turpitude, or to paſs a Complement upon it, and call it a moral Rectitude, and ſuch like fine Scholaſtick terms, invented by men at leiſure to pelt at one another, for their own diverſion, that they may admire each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and be proud of themſelves, without any real benefit or advantage to the World, without aſſigning a particular reaſon of intereſt, why we ſhould do the one or avoid the other, is as much as to ſay, a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98910:9"/> thing is good for nothing, or it is bad, but we know not why, or it is good or bad for a Womans Reaſon, becauſe it is; and this Reaſon will ſerve as well to prove, that Murder or Adultery are good things, as that they are bad ones; and ſuch as againſt which no Laws can be too ſtrict, nor any Puniſhment too exemplary, or too ſevere.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Laws of Nature therefore have every one of them their Sanction in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and in this appears the excellence of natural and of revealed Religion, that they oblige us to nothing as a Rule of Life and Practice, which, all things conſidered, is not the trueſt Intereſt of Mankind, and the Breach of which, without any particular Divine Judgment, is not ſufficiently puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it ſelf: as on the Contrary in a ſtrict and regular obſervance of thoſe wholeſome Rules, which God and Nature have tyed and bound upon us for the due Conduct and Governance of our Lives, we find the moſt perfect Eaſe and Satisfaction.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Neither is it any thing elſe that makes all kinds of Intemperance, whether in bodily Enjoyment, or in the Paſſions of the mind, unlawful, but that they are atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with ſo many, and ſo great Dangers, Troubles, and Inconveniencies to our ſelves
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98910:9"/> and others, but that they are deſtructive to our Health; that they diſcompoſe the quiet and ſerenity of our Thoughts, that they are an Obſtruction to Reaſon, an Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to Buſineſs, that they make us uſeleſs and unſerviceable to the World; that inſtead of procuring us Intereſt and Favour among men, they do always either excite their Contempt, or provoke their Diſpleaſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us; that they expoſe us to the want of Beggars, and to the ſhifts and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of deſperate men; that by the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Tumult and Hurry of our Minds, they hinder our Communion with God, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercept the gentle Influences of his bleſſed Spirit, wherein the higheſt Improvement of mortal Happineſs conſiſts; that they bring the whole World into Diſorder and Confuſion; and that as they do ever more begin in Folly, ſo they commonly end in Miſery and Diſgrace.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. And this is plainly the reaſon why the contrary Practices to theſe, are termed and accounted Laws of Nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have their own Reward and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs annext to them, and becauſe they have all of them quite contrary Effects to thoſe I have newly mentioned, and tend all of them to the Good and Advantage of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98910:10"/> Mankind in general, and of every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſon.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Charity to ſuch as are in want, and Forgiveneſs to ſuch as have offended, and an Univerſal Benevolence and good Will to the whole Creation of God, are therefore Laws as well of natural as revealed Religion, not only becauſe they procure us Friends and Alliances in the World, without which no mans life can be comfortable and eaſie; or becauſe they tend to the extinguiſhing all Quarrels and Animoſities among men, which would otherwiſe proceed without meaſure, and without end to the unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diſturbance of Mankind; but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are owing to that calm Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rament and Frame of Mind, wherein the very Nature of true Bleſſedneſs conſiſts.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Laſtly, this is the Reaſon why evil Appetites, as well as evil Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are forbidden, as well by the Law of Nature, as by that of Chriſt; becauſe Appetite hath no tendency, but to Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and therefore if the Enjoyment be forbidden, the pampering and indulging the Appetite muſt of neceſſity be ſo too. But the more immediate Reaſons why all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate Appetites are forbidden, either by the Laws of Nature, or by thoſe of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98910:10"/> Chriſt, are theſe two. Firſt, they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful upon the Compariſon, becauſe they take our Minds off from thoſe Thoughts and Deſires, in which we find greater Eaſe, Contentment, and Satisfaction to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that being enjoyed, their Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications are already ſuppoſed to be prohibited and unlawful, and being denied Enjoyment, they are but a perpetual Pain and Torment to us, and therefore we are obliged not to give them Entertainment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Principle of Self-happineſs, and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſervation, which is the very Root and Spring of all Obligation whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. For there can be no Obligation, where there is no Law; and there can be no Law, to which there is no Puniſhment annex'd; for how can that Law be binding, which it is indifferent whether we obſerve or no? as it muſt be, if there be no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Inconvenience attending the Breach of it; as on the contrary, if there be any Dammage or Inconvenience accruing, then it is manifeſt upon the ſame reaſon, by which no Inconvenience makes it no Law, that it is purely that Inconvenience or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage, together with the Reward or Happineſs annex'd to the Obſervance of it, in which the Sanction of the Law is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98910:11"/> and from which it becomes binding or obligatory to thoſe to whom it is preſcribed.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. And ſo thoſe are ſaid to be Laws of Nature whoſe Breach is attended with ſome natural Inconvenience; as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Temperance in our Diet, Moderation in our Paſſions, Juſtice in our Dealings, Conſtancy in our Friendſhips, Diligence in our Employments, Sweetneſs and Affabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in our Tempers; theſe are therefore Laws of Nature, becauſe the obſervance of them brings very ſignal, and very evident Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to men; and the contrary Diſpoſitions are partly for want of thoſe Advantages, and partly by reaſon of many Troubles and Incommodities which they bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with them, ſufficiently tormented and puniſhed by themſelves.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. And this, when matters are exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to the bottom, will be found to be the true and only difference betwixt things neceſſary, and things indifferent, that in the firſt there is a Reaſon of Intereſt, all things conſidered, why we ſhould chuſe, or why we ſhould avoid them, but in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there is not; for let an Action be never ſo indifferent, yet if any Reaſon, how ſmall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98910:11"/> ſoever, can be aſſigned, why it ſhould be done rather than let alone, it ceaſes to be indifferent, and becomes in its Proportion neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="10">X. For all that is meant by neceſſary, is, not that a man cannot help it, or that he muſt do, or avoid ſuch an Action, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will or no, for this falls in with the Opinion of thoſe, who would have all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Actions governed by an unavoidable Fate, which deſtroys the very Nature of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference, as well as of Morality and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; but by a neceſſary Action, as it is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to an Indifferent one, ſuch an Action is to be underſtood, as is more eligible to a Wiſe man, for a reaſon of Intereſt, to be done, than to be let alone; and by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Action ſuch an one is meant, as in which there is no manner of Reaſon to be aſſigned, why we ſhould chuſe one part of the Action rather than the other.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. Moreover, what hath been ſaid, may be ſtill further confirmed by a Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon that Paſſion ſo incident to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, upon the ſenſe of having acted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs, which we are uſed to call Guilt, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, or Shame; which Paſſion is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly the extorted Confeſſion of Nature
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98910:12"/> upon the wrack, and is a ſecret acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment within our ſelves, that we have done againſt our Intereſt, or that we have acted like fooliſh and unreaſonable men; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed our Repentance it ſelf would be the only thing that could be blamed, if that Behaviour of ours, which was the cauſe of it, could be juſtified by any ſubſtantial Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and certainly no better, or more ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory account of any Action can be given either to our ſelves or others, than that all things conſidered, we have acted moſt wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for our own Advantage.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. This is that which depreſſeth our Spirits, and robs us of our natural Cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Vigour, that makes us hang down our heads, and fills our minds with ſo many painful Thoughts, upon the ſenſe of having neglected, or ſwerved from our Duty into the Commiſſion of that which hath the Appearance and Character of a Crime, that we are ſenſible we have acted fooliſhly, and that we cannot reconcile what we have done to our own Intereſt, or to the Intereſt of Mankind; we are out of favour with our ſelves and others, and being deſerted and deſpiſed by all that have any value for the Reputation of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity or Prudence, we become forlorn,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98910:12"/> uſeleſs, and contemptible Creatures.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. But when we do thoſe things, which are for our own Advantage, or for the good of the Publick, in which our own ſafety and ſecurity is included, this fills us all over with a ſtrange kind of lightſomneſs and jollity of Spirit; we are at peace with our ſelves, and as far as may be, out of all apprehenſion of fear or danger from others; we rejoyce in the conſciouſneſs of having acted as becomes wiſe and underſtanding men, and we are confirmed in our Opinion of our ſelves by the Approbation of our Neighbours; and by this means we are put in a Capacity of being as powerful and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable among men, as our Condition and Circumſtances of Life and Fortune will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; and theſe things I take to be a very plain Teſtimony of Mankind and of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture her ſelf, to the truth of this Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That all Obligation is founded upon Intereſt, and that to do wiſely and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, are things in themſelves, and by the unanimous Confeſſion of both Parties, the Innocent and the Guilty, inconſiſtent with each other.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. From whence we may diſcern the Vanity and Folly of thoſe learned men, who
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98910:13"/> are uſed to talk ſo loudly of eſſential Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, and eternal Notions, and I know not what phantaſtical <hi>Idea's</hi> in an abſtracted way, whereas there is indeed nothing which is either good or bad meerly by its ſelf, but every thing which is good, is good, that is, uſeful to ſomething, and every thing which is bad, is ſo with reference to ſome Nature or other, to which it is more or leſs pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and deſtructive; from whence it follows (the nature of Obligation being a reſult ariſing from the Uſefulneſs or Hurtfulneſs of a thing propoſed to be the Object of a free Agents choice, with reſpect to that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent which is converſant about it) that all Obligation muſt be not of a ſimple, but of a compound or a concrete Nature, and muſt always have an inſeparable Reſpect to the Intereſt or Happineſs of thoſe, to whom that Obligation is binding. And it is not only true, that our Intereſt and our Duty are both of them the ſame, but that it is abſolutely impoſſible any thing ſhould be our Duty, which is not our Intereſt, into the Bargain; for no man can poſſibly be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to that, which, all things conſidered, will be to his Diſadvantage.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. Yet I do not deny, that all the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Vertues of what ſort ſoever, whether
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98910:13"/> they be Perſonal or Political, have an eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and eternal goodneſs in them, but not in that ſenſe, in which ſome Learned men, more ſpeculative &amp; ſeemingly profound then wiſe, have taken it; for if you ask them why theſe things are good or evil, all you can get from them is, that theſe things are Eternal verities, and that they are as plain, as that two and two make four, or that out of nothing comes nothing, or that both parts of a contradiction cannot be true at the ſame time, all which propoſitions are plain in themſelves, but to aſſign a reaſon of theſe things they cannot do it, and it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary they ſay that there ſhould be ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions whoſe truth muſt be diſcerned by their own light, otherwiſe men would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways argue backwards <hi>in infinitum,</hi> and there could be no ſuch thing as ſcience in World.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. But though it be very true that all demonſtration in its laſt reſult is to proceed <hi>ab indemonſtrabili,</hi> and is to be ultimately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved into ſome ſelf evident Maxim, whoſe truth in its ſelf muſt be every whit as plain and as evident to be ſeen, as the broadeſt Channel of the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Nile, when it parts and divides it ſelf into Seven ſeveral Streams, but in its cauſes as obſcure and as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98910:14"/> little underſtood as the firſt ſource and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of that wondrous River. And though it be likewiſe true, that this is the very caſe of all thoſe Propoſitions which I have newly mentioned, that they cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated by any thing more clear and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent then themſelves, yet theſe Propoſitions as they are very plain, ſo it is no wonder to find all mankind to be agreed unanimouſly in aſſenting to them, becauſe it is no mans intereſt to deny them, and therefore every man is willing to acknowledge his real ſenſe and feeling of the matter.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. But when you come to apply what hath been ſaid to moral truths, you will find a manifeſt inconvenience, in aſſerting them alſo to be of the ſame Nature with Mathematical Maxims whoſe truth as it is the cleareſt of all in it ſelf, ſo in its cauſes it is the moſt obſcure, or to give no better reaſon why theſe things are true, than on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſay they are not falſe, or they are not bad, becauſe they are eſſentially and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally good, and the inconvenience you will run will be this.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. There are a great many in the World that have a mind to be Wicked, one would gratifie his Luſt, another his Revenge,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98910:14"/> a third his Avarice, and a fourth his Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by means which are generally thought to be Unlawful; and as there are ſome that would do theſe things, and therefore would be glad of any pretence to put a good face and Colour upon what they are about, ſo there are great numbers of ſuch as have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready been actually guilty, and theſe would be every whit as glad of any excuſe to juſtifie and defend themſelves.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. And therefore when you would reprove and chide them for what they have done, or for what they intend, and yet all you can ſay for your ſelf or againſt them is, that the rules they tranſgreſs are eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially and eternally good, that they are ſo becauſe they are ſo, and becauſe it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible it ſhould be otherwiſe; this inſtead of arguing, is nothing elſe but bold affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and peremptory confidence, which may be turned upon your ſelf, for they will tell you perhaps that the charms of that which you call Vice and Wickedneſs, are equal to thoſe of Virtue, and that the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial rectitude, that is, the <hi>quelque choſe</hi> or the <hi>Je ne ſcay quoy</hi> of both, are exactly the ſame, and that it is not only true what the Stoicks of Old were uſed to affirm that <hi>omnia peccata ſunt aequalia,</hi> but alſo that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98910:15"/> monſtrous Paradox may paſs for current, that <hi>virtutes ſunt corpora,</hi> and after all they will ſay, why do you trouble your head ſo much about Vertue and Vice, when for ought you know they are the ſame, unleſs you can aſſign a difference between them.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. And that difference muſt be tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en from the effects, otherwiſe it will be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to make any ſtanding <hi>Criterium</hi> or <hi>Tekmar</hi> by which Vertue and Vice, either in the general or in particular inſtances, ſhall be diſtinguiſhed from one another; and if we will go this way to work, then I ſuppoſe it will be granted, that thoſe outward practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or thoſe inward habits and diſpoſitions of mind, which do in their own Nature tend to the diſturbance of our own happineſs, or of that of the World, are vitious and moral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evil, and becauſe the Nature of mankind is like for ever to continue the ſame, they are ſaid to be eſſentially and eternally ſo; and on the contrary by the ſame reaſon it muſt be acknowledged, that all thoſe inward affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the mind, and all thoſe external or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate activities that are derived from it, whoſe Natural tendency is to the publick or to a private good, without any damage or detriment to the publick that all theſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther practices or inclinations, are virtuous or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98910:15"/> morally good; and becauſe in their own Nature they do, and will always ſo long as mankind continues the World, continue and perſevere to be what they are, ſo highly conducible and ſo abſolutely neceſſary to the good of the World and to the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of particular perſons, becauſe they will always wherever they are found keep man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind ſteady and upright, and hinder them from doing wrong or injury to one another, they are ſaid to have an eſſential and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal rectitude in them.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. Further that this indeed is the meaſure by which we are to proceed in our diſquiſitions concerning Moral good and evil, that the intereſt and happineſs of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind is the only true, and the only infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble touchſtone to which they are to be brought for Tryal, will appear from theſe three following conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. Firſt, If Robbery and Oppreſſion, if Rapine and Injuſtice, if breach of Oaths and Promiſes, if Betraying our Truſt, or Forfeiting our Word, and breaking through all the ſacred ties and obligations of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, were things that were as much for the intereſt of the World as they are now againſt it, and tend only to bring us into
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98910:16"/> diſorder and confuſion, to make every mans Life unhappy and his ſafety precarious, and his fears endleſs: If intemperance were as much for a mans health, as it is now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive and pernicious to all the uſeful faculties both of his Body and Mind, there is no queſtion to be made but theſe things would be as Lawful and Commendable, as they are now worthy of Puniſhment or of Blame, becauſe Laws are made for nothing elſe but only for the intereſt and well being of the publick; things that are manifeſtly deſtructive to this end they puniſh, about things that are indifferent or ſignifie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing either way towards it, they do not concern themſelves, and thoſe things or perſons that are uſeful and advantageous to the publick weal, the Laws and the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of all Nations, ſo far as theſe things can be adjuſted by any common Rule or Meaſure, are uſed proportionably to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and reward; and though the other ſort of Juſtice, which conſiſts, not in the reward of Vritue, but in the Puniſhment of Wickedneſs or Vice, be that which is much more equally diſtributed than the other, yet the Meaſure of this Juſtice, being the detriment or damage accruing to the publick, and the proportion in which all puniſhments are inflicted, being altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98910:16"/> governed by this meaſure, this is a Confeſſion of all Nations and all Ages, that the meaſure of moral evil is the Intereſt of Mankind; and if all that is meant by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral evil, is, that in its own nature, or in its immediate tendency, it is hurtful to a particular perſon, or to the Commonwealth, then all that can be meant by morally good, is that, which by the conſent and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Mankind is found to be abſolutely neceſſary, or highly uſeful and expedient for it.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. Secondly, the ſame thing will appear from this, that there are ſome ſort of Actions which are not always determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately good or evil, but ſometimes one, and ſometimes the other, as the Phyſical Action is the ſame, whether I kill a man <hi>ſe defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo,</hi> or when his back was towards me, in cold blood, without any Provocation; but yet in one caſe the Law not only par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, but commends the Action; but in the other it will be ſure to revenge the Death of an innocent perſon with that of him, by whoſe unjuſt and cruel hand that mortal Wound was inflicted; and both of theſe things depend upon the ſame reaſon, becauſe it is for the Intereſt of the publick, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man could be ſecure in any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98910:17"/> where, upon an extremity he may not be ſuffered to defend himſelf, or where another with impunity may be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to hurt, annoy, or kill him without provocation; and yet theſe two Actions, though Phyſically the ſame, yet in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of them, they are extreamly diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from, nay, they are directly oppoſite and contrary to one another; and ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if a man have carnal Knowledge of his lawful Wife, it is not only a lawful thing, but a Duty; but if he commit Adultery with another mans, it is ſo far from being a Duty that it is one of the higheſt Crimes that can be committed; the reaſon is, becauſe the firſt is for the peace of every Family, and of the Commonwealth; the ſecond is a cauſe of infinite Strifes and Quarrels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a man and his Wife, a man and his Neighbour, a man and his Friend; it is an Invaſion of that barrier and boundary of Juſtice, by which every man enjoys his own, and without which no Family can be ſafe, nor any Kingdom happy; it tends to the introducing a promiſcuous Luſt, and to the rooting out that ſhame and modeſty from among men, without which the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Deſires of men will grow too ſtrong for the publick peace, and will by Degrees lanch out into all manner of Riot,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98910:17"/> Diſorder, and Exceſs; and yet the Phyſical Action of the <hi>Copula Carnalis</hi> is the ſame in the one Caſe as the other; wherefore this is another unanſwerable Demonſtration, that the Intereſt of Mankind is to be the ſquare and meaſure of Moral good or evil.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIV. But thirdly, the third and laſt thing by which I ſhall endeavour to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that all Obligation is founded in the Intereſt either of men conſidered by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or as they are Members of a Civil Society, ſhall be this, that though it be true in the General, for example, That Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and Juſtice are indiſpenſable Duties, and ſuch as are of Moral and Eternal Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, yet theſe things are not true <hi>in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſibli,</hi> as the Schools are uſed to ſpeak, but there is a manifeſt Latitude to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for the ſame thing is not intemperate in one man, that may be ſo in another, by reaſon of different Conſtitutions, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Habits of body; that may be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for one man for the preſervation of his Health, or for the carrying him with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and alacrity through his Buſineſs, which in another may be nothing elſe but the vicious Entertainment of his idle time, or the cauſe of Sickneſs and Diſeaſes to himſelf and of misfortune to his Family
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98910:18"/> and Relations; again, that may be a lawful Recreation by Wine, or Company, or Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Feeding, or innocent and harmleſs Mirth after the Fatigues of Buſineſs, and to fit and prepare us for a freſh Encounter with the Cares of Human Life, which being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly uſed, would be a ſin, becauſe it would tend to the Ruine of our ſelves and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and would render us either contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or at leaſt, uſeleſs and unſerviceable to the World; and ſo alſo as to Juſtice, it is in the general, neceſſary, that every man ſhould have his own, and, that no man ſhould wrong or abuſe another; but yet as to the particular Inſtances of this Juſtice, they are variable by Circumſtances of time, and place, and perſon; they are determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Civil Law, or by a Court of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, where the expreſs Letter of the Law will not give Relief: And to inſtance in no other Caſe, that of Preſcription is very pertinent to this Purpoſe, where ſo many Years Poſſeſſion ſhall give a man a legal Title, though his Anceſtors came wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully by that which he enjoys; the Reaſon is, becauſe, if all Claims were examined to the bottom, this might unſettle a Nation, and make a publick Diſturbance, if all the Frauds and Abuſes which our Anceſtors have committed, or all the queſtionable
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98910:18"/> Priviledges or Emoluments which they have uſurped, ſhould after a long term of peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able continuance in the Poſſeſſion of them, be called into queſtion; and therefore it is better in this Caſe, that a private Loſs be ſuſtained, than that the publick ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted by old and worn out Titles, and by Claims, which when they are ſifted to the bottom, will be found for the moſt part Vexatious and Diſhoneſt. From all which it is manifeſt, that Intereſt, either private or publick, is the ſole and entire Meaſure as well of publick as private Obligation; and that no other intelligible Principle can poſſibly be produced, that can at once ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain and vindicate, as this will do, all the <hi>Phaenomena,</hi> and all the conceaveable Inſtances that can be thought of, or alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, wherein there is any thing of Duty or Obligation.</p>
            <p n="25">XXV. I am not ignorant, that it may be objected, becauſe I have not yet obvia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that Accuſation, that by reſolving all Obligation into a Principle of Intereſt, I have cut the ſtrongeſt band of human So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety in ſunder, and that is, the mutual Faith, Confidence and Aſſurance, which the Members of every Civil Society, for the good of the whole, and of every part of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98910:19"/> it, ought always reciprocally to put in one another; but now, if Intereſt be the only Principle of Action, and if my own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt be to be conſidered in the firſt place, both of which Propoſitions I acknowledge to be of undoubted and unqueſtionable Truth, then when ever I can cheat or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud my Neighbour, if I can rob him of his Eſtate, his Honour, his Life, to reapa certain Advantage to my ſelf, without being diſcovered to have dealt unjuſtly and wrongfully by him; if a man abuſes himſelf or tempts another to joyn with him in any wicked Act of Intemperance or luſt in Idleneſs or Wantonneſs, and Miſ-employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of time, which might be ſpent to better and nobler purpoſes for our own good, and for the good of others; yet if this can paſs off without Notice or Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if we can commit the ſin, ſo as to conceal the ſhame, or hinder any notorious Prejudice that ſhall accrue to us, as a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of it; all this, according to my Principles, is lawful.</p>
            <p n="26">XXVI. But it would be more tolerable for <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> nay, for <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> themſelves at the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than for me, if this were my Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Piety, and my Whole Duty of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98910:19"/> Man; if this, and no more than this, were all the Doctrine of Duty and Obedience to the Laws of God, and right Reaſon which I pretend to teach; and therefore to this I anſwer, That thoſe ſins of ours, which are the moſt ſecret and concealed from the Eyes of man, and from the publick notice of the World, are yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding every whit as fooliſh and unreaſonable in themſelves, and as much, nay, perhaps more againſt our Intereſt, than thoſe which are more open and better known to the World; for the Diſgrace and Prejudice which we ſuffer in our Aſtairs, the contempt which is brought upon our perſons, and the Damage accruing to our Fortunes by a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, are though not a Puniſhment ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, yet ſuch as, perhaps, God upon our Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance will accept as a Satisfaction and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement for the Crime committed; and are beſides, not unfrequently, a means of our Amendment and Reformation of life, which is the only true way of reconciling us to God, to men, and to our ſelves; but where the Juſtice of man cannot reach us, where no viſible Puniſhment purſues the Guilty, there it is more than probable, that the Divine Judgment and Vengeance will take place, it being very unreaſonable to believe, that that all-ſeeing Eye back'd
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98910:20"/> and aſſiſted by an Almighty Arm, will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſo much Wickedneſs and Preſumption together, (when we pleaſe our ſelves with an Opinion that we are ſafe, becauſe we can hide our Crimes from the Notice and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of men) without avenging it with that Severity and Juſtice which it deſerves; and though God Almighty in this World ſhould not viſit us by any Supernatural Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from above, yet that very ſecrecy which is ſo ſweet, that it gives a new reliſh and guſto to the ſin, proves nothing but ſorrow and bitterneſs in the end, and by being a Temptation to us to proceed in the ſame Courſes that we have begun, the Conſequence of this, is, That we are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered at the laſt with ſo much the greater Infamy and Diſgrace for having lain ſo long and ſo ſecurely concealed.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. And as to the matter of Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or Oppreſſion, let the Crime we have committed be never ſo ſecret, yet I hope it will be granted at leaſt, that there is a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility that it may come abroad; and upon that Suppoſition there are theſe following things to be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. Firſt, if we be ever diſcovered, we do by this means proclaim our ſelves to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98910:20"/> be the common Enemies of Mankind; for he that will rob, defraud, or oppreſs one man, will do it to another for the ſame Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; and certainly no man can be eaſie in himſelf, when he is expoſed to the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Execrations of all that know or have any thing to do with him, no more than his Ear can be delighted with an unpleaſant ſound, or his Palate with an ungrateful taſte; and ſince the good Opinion of our Neighbours inveſts us with a real Power, and their bad one always renders us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible and weak, this might be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to perſwade us, for the ſake of ſome preſent Advantage, not to run the hazard of being obnoxious to the publick Juſtice for the preſent, or to the Contempt and Hatred of the World for all our life time after.</p>
            <p n="29">XXIX. Secondly, in all the Inſtances of injuſtice to our Neighbour, there is great danger of our being diſcovered, becauſe they have another perſon for their immediate Object, and ſo they do almoſt unavoidably betray themſelves.</p>
            <p n="30">XXX. Thirdly, though they ſhould be concealed, yet they fill us with perpetual Jealouſies and Suſpicions, we are always
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98910:21"/> upon our watch, afraid of our own thoughts, and our own ſhadows. And we are apt to read a Diſcovery in mens Looks or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, who know nothing of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, till we betray our ſelves by a too ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous care of keeping concealed.</p>
            <p n="31">XXXI. And yet fourthly, though we were never ſo ſecure of keeping concealed, yet is it a perpetual pain and diſquiet to a mans mind, to have been guilty of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, which he dares not own, though the Jealouſies which attend all injuſtice could be laid aſleep, yet the Guilt of it cannot, that will be always preſent to our minds, and will perpetually interrupt the quiet of our Thoughts; for Baſeneſs or Injuſtice and Happineſs are incompatible together, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is any man thoroughly at eaſe, who cannot juſtifie whatever he hath done to himſelf, as well as to others, but ſo much as he falls ſhort of perfect Innocence, ſo much he muſt needs want of perfect Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs alſo.</p>
            <p n="32">XXXII. Fifthly, it is impoſſible any man who is guilty of theſe Practiſes, ſhould be perfectly reconciled to himſelf, becauſe out of a ſenſe of his own Happineſs, and out of a natural deſire of ſelf-preſervation, he
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98910:21"/> muſt unavoidably hate and deteſt them in another; and this is a moſt certain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth, that no man can poſſibly be happy, who cannot approve his own Actions to himſelf.</p>
            <p n="33">XXXIII. Sixthly, either ſuch Practices are grown habitual in any man, or they are not; if the latter, then the reaſon why he does not continue in the ſame bad Courſes which he hath begun, is, becauſe he feels ſome check and reſtraint upon his mind, and he is troubled for what is paſt; and for the ſame reaſon it had been much better for him, if he had never been guilty at all; for by happineſs nothing elſe being meant, but a mind that is perfectly quiet and at eaſe from bodily pain, and from Diſcontent and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh in it ſelf, it is manifeſt, that Guilt and Happineſs are inconſiſtent together.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Horar. Ep. l. 1. ad Lol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium.</note>Non domus &amp; fundus, non aeris acervus &amp; auri,</l>
               <l>Aegroto domini deduxit corpore febres,</l>
               <l>Non animo curas, valeat poſſeſſor oportet,</l>
               <l>Si comportatis rebus bene cogitat uti.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>But on the other ſide, if a man be hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a long courſe of ſin into a deſperate habit of perſiſting in it without regret, it
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98910:22"/> is uſually ſeen, that this is not done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out abundance of violence to the natural grain and byaſs of his mind, and beſides morally impoſſible, but he will ſome time or other be made a publick example of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, Contempt, and Shame.</p>
            <p n="34">XXXIV. Seventhly, it is worth out while to conſider, that ſuch Practiſes as theſe are in their example pernicious to our ſelves, if ever they come to be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and known; for this is the nature of Examples, that they are more eaſily imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, than they are given; and therefore whoever claims, or ſeizes, or poſſeſſes any thing unjuſtly, whoever deals perſidiouſly or falſely with his Neighbour, he does in effect but teach others to do the ſame by him. He does what lies in his power to corrupt and debauch the World into a ſtate of Hoſtility, and publick Rapine, and to hinder himſelf from enjoying what he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes with ſecurity and eaſe.</p>
            <p n="35">XXXV. Eighthly and Laſtly, we are to conſider that thoſe injuries which are done to our Neighbour, do much more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate and provoke mankind againſt us, than thoſe which we commit againſt our ſelves, theſe upon amendment will eaſily
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98910:22"/> find forgiveneſs, becauſe none but our ſelves receive any prejudice by them any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than by the bare example, which it is at the choice of others either to imitate or let alone, as they pleaſe themſelves, but when we wrong or abuſe another man, this makes all People for ever after to ſtand upon their guard, and to be very cautious of have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing to do with us, for fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought into a ſnare; they will never be perſuaded that the man hath chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Principles, but he will always be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, never truſted, wherever he may get any the leaſt advantage by deceit or by oppreſſion, and though his repentance be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo hearty and ſyncere, yet the memory of his paſt injuſtice will always be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible prejudice and diſadvantage to him, in all his deſigns and undertakeings. And what can be more raſh and inconſiderate, than for a man to part with his happineſs, which conſiſts in his own good opinion of himſelf, and with his intereſt, which is founded in the good opinion of others, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any conſideration whatſoever, though ſeemingly of never ſuch preſent advantage, when it hath ſo much bitterneſs and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet at the bottom? This certainly is a bargain much more fooliſh, than that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal exchange of <hi>Glaucus</hi> and <hi>Diomedes.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:98910:23"/>
            <p n="36">XXXVI. And as the diſadvantages that accrue to men that have contracted a load of guilt by their injuſtice or oppreſſion are great, the diſquiet certain, the fears infinite, and the dangers dreadful to all that have not loſt all ſenſe of modeſty and ſhame, which is it ſelf a diſeaſe of human Nature, and is puniſhed ſufficiently by it ſelf, and by the contempt and hatred which it certainly draws after it; ſo are the advantages that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the contrary diſpoſitions and practices every whit as conſiderable both to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and to particular perſons;<note place="margin">Prov. 14. 34.</note> 
               <hi>Righteouſneſs exalteth a Nation,</hi> ſaid <hi>Solomon, but ſin is a reproach to any people;</hi> all manner of Vice, but more eſpecially that ſort of it which conſiſts in want of Juſtice, Mercy, or Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to our Neighbours, of Gratitude to our Friends, Duty to our Parents, Loyalty to our Prince, does as Naturally tend to the ruin of the Body Politick, as Poiſon and Diſeaſes to that of the Natural, they are bigg with ſtrife, and they go laden with nothing but Miſchief and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but Righteouſneſs, that is, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant exerciſe of all theſe publick Virtues, is that which makes a Nation great and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, happy at home and great abroad, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon other Nations with a formidable aſpect, and with a pleaſing one upon it ſelf,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98910:23"/> and as the perfection of theſe vertues run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning through all the Veins and Veſſels of the Civil Body, may be called its utmoſt health and life, and vigour, ſo is the decay of them a proportionable ſickneſs and diſeaſe, and the final baniſhment or total abſence of them may be call'd its death; for it cannot certainly be doubted, if men were generally without pitty on the one hand and without gratitude on the other, but this muſt needs extremely looſen and unty the bands of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſociety, and produce a ſtrange cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and indifference in men to one another, if there were no Truth in mens words, no Faith in their dealings, no Security for the moſt perfect innocence from the malevolence of ſlanderous and calumniating Tongues, if not only our faults ſhould be aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated beyond their due extent, but even our beſt actions miſrepreſented, if Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Power were the only Meaſure of Action, and if neither any mans perſon nor his eſtate were ſecure from violence and rapine, it would be impoſſible that the World ſhould ſubſiſt one moment, but all things muſt immediately run into diſorder and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</p>
            <p n="37">XXXVII. Again what hath been ſaid of the Social or Political Vices, ſuch as of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98910:24"/> the immediate inconvenience of which, our Neighbour is the Object, the ſame may be ſaid alſo of all perſonal enormities, or of thoſe Vices whoſe immediate damage, ſeparated from the blaſting influence of their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, terminates in our ſelves, that they carry their own Puniſhment along with them, and though they be never ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed, yet, for all that, my principles do not make them Lawful, for that only is Naturally Lawful which hath no Natural inconvenience attending it, and that is Naturally of the higheſt Obligation which carries along with it the greateſt Natural recompence and reward, for as to that which is indifferent, that is, which hath neither advantage or inconvenience going along with it, I may do as I pleaſe and am by Nature left as undetermined, as the thing it ſelf is, which is propoſed to me, as the Object of my choice; but when on the one ſide it hath a Natural Puniſhment attending it, and on the other a Natural Reward, theſe are the Signatures and Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of a Law, and theſe Rewards and Puniſhments proceeding not from the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a mortal Judge, or from the hand of an Executioner, Bailiff or Beadle, but from the Immortal and Eternal Nature and tendency of things themſelves, the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98910:24"/> Puniſhment will as certainly tread upon the heels of the crime, as effects follow their cauſes, though no man elſe have any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it, or be at all ſenſible of thoſe pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful conſequences of an immoral Action or a wicked life, which Nature intended only for the Offender himſelf.</p>
            <p n="38">XXXVIII. Intemperance and luſt though ſmothered up in never ſo proſound and deep a ſilence, will yet notwithſtanding be ſure to have their Natural Effects both upon our Bodies and Minds, and by that means they will betray us at laſt, though we mannage our buſineſs with never ſo much cunning and though we keep our own council never ſo well, the Gout and Stone may tell tales though we hold our peace, and Dropſies and Conſumptions will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their own cauſes, and the ſins of thoſe that are affected with them, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, as it is hardly to be believed that it is that habituall wickedneſs ſhould be a ſecret to the world.</p>
            <p n="39">XXXIX. But though our Vices ſhould not prevail ſo far, as to bring any ſuch painful or<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> languiſhing diſeaſe upon us, yet
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98910:25"/> there are other Natural Puniſhments far ſhort of this, that will expreſs our ſhame, the dullneſs of a mans countenance, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>activity and want of uſual briskneſs in his mind, the decay of his Natural parts and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities for buſineſs, or inquiries into truth, the dumpiſhneſs of his Spirit, the Deject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of his looks, the want of that cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and Vivacity of Spirit which is the effect of innocence and the reward of it, theſe do at once betray and puniſh him, as well from abroad, as at home within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; he loſes his intereſt and gets diſgrace into the bargain from without, good men ſhun him and even the moderately bad have no Delight and Pleaſure in his converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and this is common to all that have been very guilty in any kind, but more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of Treachery, Deceitfulneſs, and Injuſtice, that they hang down their Heads, they are aſhamed of the Day, and afraid of the Sun, they dread the very appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a good man, and they take but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle pleaſure in the company of one another.</p>
            <p n="40">XL. For it is ſo ordered by divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence for the good of the World, that as there are Natural Puniſhments even from without, that do as conſtantly follow wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and unlawful courſes, as the ſhade haunts
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98910:25"/> the light or light follows the Sun, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural rewards, that are with no leſs conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and certainty annext to every thing that hath the name and eſteem of good and virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous among men, ſo there is alſo antecedent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to any of thoſe outward effects, an inward calm and ſerenity of mind while it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues in innocence, there is a harmony and agreement between it ſelf and Virtue, though no reward from without ſhould ever be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, it injoyes it ſelf in the ſenſe of its own Brightneſs and untainted Beauty; and there is a congruity between that and goodneſs, which being once broken, there ariſes preſently a ſenſe of pain, as trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and vexatious to the mind, as the breaking of a Bone or the diſlocation of any Joynt or Member in the Body, the Soul is ruffled diſturbed and diſcompoſed, and the Muſick being ſpoilt, to which it was uſed to dance, it hears nothing now but harſh and unpleaſant ſounds, which put it into a diſorderly and unequal Motion.</p>
            <p n="41">XLI. Moreover, the ſame merciful and gracious Being, that hath with ſo much ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs provided for the happineſs of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons, by enduingthem with ſuch natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral tendencies to goodneſs, after all the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſtical</hi> Declamations of the Pravity and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98910:26"/> Beaſtlineſs of human nature, and with ſuch Paſſions as ſhame and Sorrow, and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for the Puniſhment of our ſins, and for an Example to others, and for the reſtoring us to the primitive health and integrity of our minds, (it being but neceſſary, that the Wound ſhould be ſearched, before it can be healed) hath alſo endued every man more or leſs, with a ſenſe of Pity and Compaſſion for others of whoſe Sufferings we are made ſenſible by a certain Sympathy and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Nature, that we may give our ſelves caſe by doing good, and that we may be helpful and ſubſervient to the Intereſt and Happineſs of each other; for God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty knew very well, that no man could ſubſiſt by himſelf, neither would it have been ſo much for the Happineſs of human life, that we ſhould have been able to do it, the Comforts of Friendſhip and mutual Obligation being far preferrable to the ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Self-happineſs of an Independent State in any, but an infinitely perfect Being, who hath all Goodneſs and Bleſſedneſs in himſelf; and therefore it is certain, that when, upon a fit occaſion offered, we ſhut up our Hearts from relieving the Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our Brother in Affliction or Pain, and ſtifle this Divine ſenſe of Pity and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, which is moſt prevalent in Wiſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98910:26"/> men, and which (if it be not wholly ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that cauſe) is in part at leaſt the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of a Reflection upon the uncertainty of human Affairs, is at once a great ſin, and a grievous Folly together; it proceeds from want of skill, in the true ſtate of the World, and from want of a due Submiſſion to that Almighty Will and Power in the perſon of our Brother, which may, when it pleaſes, inflict the ſame Calamities or Wants, upon our own.</p>
            <p n="42">XLII. It is very clear from the nature of things themſelves, that there is a Connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt Hunger and its proper Food, betwixt Sickneſs and thoſe Medicines which are provided by nature for its Cure; we have all of us the ſame Appetites, and the ſame Organs fitted and intended by Nature for the ſame uſes; and therefore we muſt all of us be ſuppoſed to have a natural right to all thoſe neceſſary Enjoyments, which tend to the Maintenance and Preſervation of life, neither can any man pretend a right to Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity, that is, to that of which he is in no abſolute need, or to that of which he makes no uſe, when the Neceſſities of his Neighbour call upon him to part with it for his Relief, for this is to abuſe the Gifts of Fortune againſt the intention of Nature,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98910:27"/> who hath provided ſufficiently for all, and intended, that all the Wants of her Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſhould be ſupplied out of her abundant Store.</p>
            <p n="43">XLIII. Beſides, that thoſe Powers and Faculties which we find within our ſelves, as well of Body as Mind, were not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by God and Nature meerly for our own uſe, but for the mutual Benefit and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of each other, as is plain from this That they are ſo plainly fitted for that purpoſe, as ſit as the eye is for ſeeing, or the ear for hearing; and therefore he that ſeeing another reduced to any Extremity or Want, ſhall ſtand lazy and unactive by, when it is in his power to help him, does manifeſtly betray that truſt, which God and Nature have repoſed in him, by giving him that ſtrength of Body, and thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of Mind, which are ſo exactly fitted for the mutual aid and aſſiſtance of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="44">XLIV. Not that we are to ſpend our whole ſtrength, and to lay out all our Thoughts in a ſollicitous Proviſion for the ſafety or ſubſiſtance of others; for we are in the firſt place to conſult our own Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which is inconſiſtent with a too ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98910:27"/> carking for our ſelves, and much more for others; and beſides, a very ſmall Proportion of every mans care and time will be ſufficient in order to this end.</p>
            <p n="45">XLV. Neither are we obliged to ſquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der away our whole Eſtates in charitable uſes, becauſe they ceaſe to be Charitable, when we are ſo unkind to our ſelves; and becauſe an Univerſal Practice of ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeneſs, would introduce an equality of Order and Power, and conſequently an U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Anarchy and Confuſion, into the World, which is very inconſiſtent with the Quiet and Happineſs of it; but it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in this caſe, if a man ſhall contribute ſuch a reaſonable <hi>quota</hi> or Proportion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the relief of thoſe that are in want, as may be ſufficient, if imitated by others, in their ſeveral Capacities and Abilities of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, to ſupply all the real Wants and Neceſſities of Mankind; but if any man will do more than this comes to, ſo he do no prejudice to his Family and Relations, for <hi>Charity begins at home,</hi> all the harm he will get, will be, that he will have the greater ſatisfaction in himſelf, the greater praiſe from men, and the more exceeding Recompence of Reward from God, who ſees his Charity, and approves the Image of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98910:28"/> his own Goodneſs drawn in little by the Bounty of his Creatures and Servants to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards each other.</p>
            <p n="46">XLVI. And if an evil day ſhould happen to overtake him, he will find, that this is but <hi>caſting his bread upon the waters,</hi> from whence it will be ſure to return again with plenty, and flow in upon him with a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtream; becauſe, beſides the Providence of God, which does not ordinarily fail to make a ſutable Proviſion for Virtue in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and will not eaſily deſert or aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who hath been ſo great an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Mercy and Compaſſion to others, ſuch is the nature of man likewiſe impreſs'd upon him by the Divine Wiſdom and Goodneſs, for the better preſervation and maintenance of his nobleſt Creature, that you ſhall find but very few, who have not ſome ſenſe of Gratitude about them, or who will not charitably and affectionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remember what we have done for them, when we are able to do no more for our ſelves; and therefore we ſhall be ſure to find, to our exceeding Comfort and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, that the Alms and Charities which others have begged of us, will interceed on our behalf from whence they came, with an Importunity not to be reſiſted, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98910:28"/> they whom we have relieved, will themſelves return the Kindneſs; or if they are not able, yet others will the ſooner do it for their ſakes; and the naked whom we have clothed, the hungry whom we have fed, the Kindneſſes and Civilities which we have ſhewn to all that have ſtood in need of our aſſiſtance, will plead more ſtrongly on our behalf, than all the crafty Rhetorick of the moſt importunate, and moſt practis'd Beggar.</p>
            <p n="47">XLVII. Wherefore all theſe Inſtincts and Paſſions of the human Nature, which I have lately mentioned, being ſo wiſely and ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully contrived for our own preſervation, and for the mutual aſſiſtance of each other, are plain and manifeſt Indications of a Divine Providence governing the World, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intending human Affairs; and therefore I am ſo far from extending this Principle of Intereſt no further than the publick view of the World, that I think, for any man to do ſo, is the moſt fooliſh and Unphiloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical thing that can be conceived; for ſince we can neither look into our ſelves, nor abroad into the World, but we find all things ſo full of Uſefulneſs and Beauty, ſince there is Nouriſhment and Suſtenance provided round about us for our Bodies, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98910:29"/> ſince the Organization and Contexture of our own, as well as of the Bodies of other Animals, is ſo exquiſitely fitted to digeſt and aſſimilate that Nouriſhment into it ſelf, ſince there is every where ſuch plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Proviſion made, not only for the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, but for the Pleaſures of life, ſince there is in all Animals a natural deſire of maintaining and propagating their ſeveral Kinds; ſince there is ſo much wiſe Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, and wonderful Curioſity in the ſpermatick or proliſick Parts and Veſſels for the accompliſhing the ends of Nature, ſince there is in all Creatures, not excepting the moſt ſluggiſh and inſenſible of Beaſts themſelves, a natural Tenderneſs and Fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the Preſervation of their reſpective Broods, which would otherwiſe be expoſed to Want and Hunger, to the Injuries of the weather, and to the ravenous Voracity of their fellow Creatures, of which ſo very uſeful and ſo neceſſary Affection, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to give any Phyſical or Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal account, ſince there are ſuch Paſſions, as Pity and Generoſity, not only in men, but in their degree in other Animals like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the preſervation and aſſiſtance of each other, which Paſſions it is our Intereſt to gratifie, and we are uneaſie ſometimes to our ſelves, unleſs we do it, ſince there are
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98910:29"/> alſo in the VVorld ſo many Particular Friendſhips reſulting from an unaccountable Harmony and Agreement of particular tempers, by which mens minds are ſoftned and rendred more fit and pliable for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and Society with one another, to the unſpeakable Emolument and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of Mankind; what can be more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, than to infer from the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe things, which it is altogether inconceivable they ſhould either begin, or be continued by chance, that there is a wiſe, powerful and gracious Being, by which this Univerſe is made, governed, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported? A Being which is infinitely delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, firſt, with the Exiſtence or Being, and then with the Happineſs and Preſervation of his Creatures; and that therefore upon the ſame eſſential Conſtitution of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by which he is ſo good and gracious in himſelf, he will much leſs ſuffer Injuſtice in his Creatures, thoſe eſpecially, which are not only the work of his hands, but alſo the Image and Reſemblance of his Nature, that he will ſeverely puniſh thoſe Vices, which tend to the Diſturbance and Diſquiet of the World, as all Acts of Injuſtice in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and in their Conſequences do; and that he will be ſure to reward thoſe neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and uſeful Virtues, which tend to the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98910:30"/> Peace, and Order, and good Government of it; and ſo it is uſually ſeen, that Eſtates gotten by falſhood and Injuſtice do ſeldom thrive, and that all notorious Malefactors are ſooner or later made Examples of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice and Vengeance, to the World.</p>
            <p n="48">XLVIII. And the ſame is likewiſe very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to conclude of Perſonal, as well as of Political Vices, becauſe theſe by their Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are political too, and do a publick Miſchief to the World; and becauſe thoſe natural Puniſhments, which are annex'd to Intemperance or immoderate Luſt, are to be looked upon as ſo many Admonitions of Nature, and ſo many calls from the Divine Goodneſs, whoſe very Chaſtiſements are an Argument of his love, to Repentance, and Reformation and Amendment of life; which Admonitions, if frequently reſiſted, it is very highly rational to believe, not only for the hurt we do our ſelves, but others too by our evil Example, that ſo much Goodneſs and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in Confederacy together, will not ſuffer ſuch obſtinate and unreclaimable Wickedneſs to go unpuniſhed, eſpecially if we conſider, that our Souls, as all cogitant or thinking Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingsmuſt be, are of an immaterial, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of an immortal and unfading Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and that if we carry a load of Guilt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98910:30"/> and Shame with us out of this World, we ſhall be ſure to bring it along with us into the other, which when the Divertiſements of Senſe and Company are over, will, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the acceſſion of any other Torment, be a ſufficient Puniſhment in it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="49">XLIX. And here is the great flaw in Mr. <hi>Hobs</hi> his Principles, who by not taking in the exiſtence of a God and of that Juſtice by which he governs and orders all things which he hath made, into his Politicks; hath deſtroyed the main Band and Cement of Obligation, and opened the Floodgates for a Deluge of ſecret ſin to enter in and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelm the World, nay, and the moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Villanies, if they can but be ſafe from the Juſtice of the Laws, or the Revenge of men, are, according to his Principles, lawful; whereas though it be indeed true, that Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs or Self-preſervation are the true, and perhaps the only Principles by which a virtuous or wiſe man ought to proceed, yet it is equally true, that upon this very Principle, no man ought to do any thing which is againſt the publick Intereſt and Quiet of the World, and which by woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thoſe natural Inſtincts, and Tendences to Goodneſs which he finds within himſelf, are no leſs manifeſtly againſt his own; ſo
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98910:31"/> certain it is, what the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Pſal. 111. 10.</note> that <hi>the fear of the Lord is the beginning of Wiſdom,</hi> that is, it is the foundation of Vertue and the very root and baſis of all obligation; and therefore this is the true difference betwixt a Fool and a Knave, a Fool is he that doth not proceed upon any prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Intereſt, at all, a Knave is he that does wrong upon a principle of Intereſt, but he does not take his whole Intereſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo at the long run is a Fool too as well as the other, though in his own conceit he be wonderful Wiſe.</p>
            <p n="50">L. I am really of opinion not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that all the Duties of common life, but all the duties of Religion too<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are founded upon Intereſt as their only true baſis and bottom, and that all things conſidered, it is very true that no man would be obliged to <hi>fear</hi> or ſerve <hi>God for nought,</hi> for as for love and admiration, the one of the divine goodneſs, the other of the excellence and perfection of his Nature, theſe are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Religious Duties, but things extorted from us, whether we will or no, by the lovelineſs and excellence of the Object we converſe with, and it is the ſame thing proportionably in any other Object, bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence and good Nature do unavoidably
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98910:31"/> unite and attract us to themſelves, where ever we meet with them, and ſo does all excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence extort a proportionable wonder and admiration from us; only this indeed I do not deny, that it is our duty to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate much upon the Divine Wiſdom and Power, and to indeavour all we can to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame and kindle in our minds every day and hour a ſtronger and a more paſſionate Love for his goodneſs, and gratitude for his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to us, but we are not obliged to this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any other ſcore than only becauſe it is our intereſt, for God is a very pleaſing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to converſe with, a Noble Pattern for our imitation, and by meditating fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently upon the Power and Juſtice, as well as the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of his Nature, the root of Obligation which begins in him and from thence diffuſeth it ſelf and ſends an wholeſome and refreſhing ſap through all the ſeveral branches and members of the Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual World, hath always the ſtronger influence and operation upon our minds, and produceth effects agreeable to it ſelf in our lives and converſations.</p>
            <p n="52">LII. The remaining parts of Religion which have not been yet conſidered, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prayer for the good things we want, to him that is alone able to ſupply all the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98910:32"/> and cravings of our Nature, or thankſgiving for what we have received, to him whom we cannot chuſe but love for all his repeated inſtances of unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able goodneſs and mercy, (and in that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Love, we our ſelves find an infinite ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and contentment) to him that can give us more, and to him that can withdraw when he pleaſes what he hath already given, or elſe laſtly it is Confeſſion and Repentance of our ſins to him whom we have Juſtly incenſed and provoked againſt us by the commiſſion of them, and who may when he pleaſes take the advantage of us and diſplay his juſtice in the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Offences, as well as ſhow his Mercy by their Forgiveneſs, and that all theſe Duties are founded in ſelf intereſt cannot certainly be queſtioned, when it appears ſo plainly, that their only end and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is either to procure us ſome good or to avert ſome impending evil from falling upon our Heads.</p>
            <p n="53">LIII. This is all the harm of Idolatry and ſuperſtition, not that God can be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by any thing we do, or that any poor acknowledgments and praiſes of ours can add any thing to the bleſſedneſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of his Nature, but becauſe theſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98910:32"/> two are the Diſeaſes of the mind, and tend very much to the debaſing of our Spirits by Servile ſlatteries, and cauſeleſs fears and it would be all one to God, what ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we had concerning him, if it were not that thoſe which are the trueſt and the moſt like that being which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent, are Naturally fitted to ennoble and exalt our Natures, and to make us good and uſeful men to our ſelves and to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and if it were not that Idolatry and Polytheiſm do ſo Naturally lead men to a beliefe that there is no God at all, and do by conſequence deſtroy the Firſt principle of Obligation, without a due regard to which it is impoſſible for human ſociety to ſubſiſt, and if it were not that ſuperſtition by pretending to appeaſe Gods wrath by triſling expiations and ridiculous rites, gives a kind of Licence to Wickedneſs in the World, and is it ſelf an indulgence to all manner of Vice, without the help of the Pontifical Chair, from whence the Pope diſpenſes Pardons among all that have Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to purchaſe them at his hands, and no ſin is ſo mortal as to be miſerably poor.</p>
            <p n="54">LIV. I ſhall conclude this diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Laws of Nature by ſhewing the uſefulneſs of thoſe Principles upon which I
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98910:33"/> proceed, by applying them very briefly to the three greateſt controverſies that our times afford, that is, to ſay, the matter of Ceremonies and ſet Forms in religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, of Epiſcopal ſuperiority in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, and of paſſive obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence where active cannot lawfully be given to the Civil State.</p>
            <p n="55">LV. For the Firſt of theſe that is the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimonies of the Church, ſince it hath been proved ſo plainly that the Intereſt of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind is the meaſure of Obligation, ſince it is neceſſary in all publick adminiſtrations whatſoever, eſpecially in the affairs of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which ought to be carry'd with the greateſt gravity and decency of all others whatſoever, ſince men are ſo apt to fall out about theſe matters if they be not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted, ſince all religious quarrels are of all others the moſt dangerous and the moſt laſting, ſince there is no end of excepting againſt Lawful things, unleſs it can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as it is not pretended, that any of the things enjoyned are in themſelves Unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; from hence it follows plainly, though this or that Ceremony be never ſo indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, yet an uniformity in the general is of abſolute neceſſity, and this in a few words is an unanſwerable Juſtification of the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98910:33"/> Church of <hi>England,</hi> and is much more in its defence then all its Enemies have ever ſaid againſt it.</p>
            <p n="56">LVI. Secondly, as for the Buſineſs of Epiſcopal Superiority, beſides that I ſhall prove elſewhere, That it was that very Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to which our Saviour himſelf, and his Diſciples and Apoſtles ſubmitted, though the Apoſtolical Pretenders of our days think much to do it. I ſay, beſides this, its lawfulneſs follows plainly from its ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, for it depends upon the very nature of Government, which if a Subordination in the State be moſt for its health and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, there is no reaſon why it ſhould not be ſo in the Church too; and you may almoſt as well ſuppoſe, that it would be the beſt form of Civil Government, that all Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſhould be no more than Petty-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, as that no Eccleſiaſtick ſhould be any no more than a Presbyter; and though it be confeſſed, that this is moſtly the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in foreign Churches, yet it is certain, that upon many accounts it comes much ſhort of Epiſcopacy for all the ends of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment that can be aſſigned, for this Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority, of Dignity, and Power, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, gives greater Encouragement to Learning, and greater eſteem to the perſons
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98910:34"/> of the Clergy, which it is for the Intereſt of every Nation, that they ſhould be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſpected; it preſerves the inferiour Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in a dutiful dependance upon thoſe that are above them, and they themſelves do ſeem the more venerable and worthy of Reſpect by the comely Obedience and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which they pay to their Betters; it is the beſt Remedy againſt Faction, the beſt Expedient againſt Hereſie, and the fartheſt Remove from Independent Congregations, which are the very top and perfection of Diſorder, and produce infinite and unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Miſchiefs both in Church and State.</p>
            <p n="57">LVII. Laſtly, for paſſive Obedience, it is therefore a Duty in Caſes, where active cannot be given, becauſe the Inconvenience to Mankind is leſs than that of every mans being Judge for himſelf, and there is no <hi>Medium</hi> between theſe two, though they are at a great diſtance from one another; for the firſt is the height of Loyalty and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, the latter makes Obedience it ſelf a precarious thing, and is always upon the very brink and border of Rebellion, and this I think is in a ſhort Compaſs, a very ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Anſwer to the late Infamous Writer of <hi>Julian the Apoſtate,</hi> who, I cannot won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that he is applauded by the <hi>Calviniſtical</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:98910:34"/> Tribe, for they that make God an arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Being, and all human Actions to be neceſſary and fatal, are paſt obeying any, but themſelves, and may ee'n do and ſay what they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>And thus much in General of the Laws of Nature.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
